Master.
老师
Lejun is awake.
乐君醒了
Lejun told me a story,
乐君告诉学生一个故事
but it's too bizarre.
可这故事太过离奇了
It's hard to believe.
难以置信
I hope you could clarify it for me.
还请老师解惑
Lejun said
乐君说
I'm not Prince Qi's son
我非岐王之子
but your son.
而是老师的儿子
Is it true?
果真吗
Take a rest.
歇会儿吧
Have some ginseng soup to strengthen your body.
喝点参汤补补身子
It'll be another tough few days.
这几日你还有的熬呢
Fortunately,
还好
the ointment Ruisheng made works well.
蕊生调的药膏效果不错
The swelling has gone down a lot.
红肿消下去了不少了
How could the Grand Tutor bear to do this?
这太傅如何下得去手的
And this.
还有这个
Anmin asked me to bring this to you.
这是大哥让我带给你的
He said he has nothing to offer
大哥说他别的东西没有
but an abundance of soft cushions
让人坐着 跪着
that can make sitting and kneeling
能舒服一点的软垫
more comfortable.
倒是有不少
Pad your knees with this.
把这个垫在膝盖下面
It'll ease the pain.
可以舒服很多
Don't worry.
你别担心
Prince Jing'an's Mansion will always be your home.
靖安王府永远都是你的家
You can stay here
你想住到什么时候
as long as you want.
就住到什么时候
Thank you, Yuanji.
多谢元姬阿姊
And Anmin too.
多谢萧大哥
My Lady, it's cold at night.
女郎 夜晚天凉
Don't catch a cold.
别着风寒了
Isn't this the fox fur cloak His Highness hunted
这是世子前几年
and made himself a few years ago?
亲自打的狐裘吧
His Highness asked me to get it.
是世子让我取的
Why didn't he bring it himself?
为何他不自己送过来
And this ointment too.
还有这药膏也是
He requested Ruisheng to
不也是他特意嘱咐蕊生
make it for you,
给你调制的
but he just won't come himself.
偏偏自己人又不来
Maybe
或许
he's afraid to see me.
是他不敢见我吧
What?
什么
Nothing.
没什么
Yuanji,
元姬阿姊
I can keep watch here myself.
这里我守着就好
Please go back and rest.
你回去歇息吧
Take care of yourself.
你自己保重
When the Phoenix Heart Tokens appear, peace shall be restored in the world.
雀骨出 天下定
How are the Phoenix Heart Tokens
这雀骨令到底如何
linked to the minerals?
与矿藏有关
Your Highness,
世子
I bought the pear blossom candy from Chengyi Hall.
诚意斋的梨花糖买来了
Deliver it to Lady Xie.
给谢娘子送过去吧
I heard she's been keeping vigil for 3 days,
听闻谢娘子守灵三日
eaten or drunk nothing
水米未进
except some ginseng soup.
只喝了些参汤
Aren't you going to see her?
世子不去看看吗
Consort Yuanji and Madam Ruisheng
世子妃和蕊夫人
visit her often.
时常去陪着
You're at least Lady Xie's
您至少是谢娘子
husband in name,
名义上的夫君
and haven't divorced.
尚未和离
It's understandable for you to
您替郡主守孝
observe mourning for her.
也在情理之中
I doubt she wants to see me right now.
她眼下未必想要见到我
Then this time,
那这回
shall I ask the Princess to deliver it?
托王妃送过去
Hang on.
等一下
Your Highness.
世子
Is she alright?
她没事吧
My Lady has fallen asleep.
女郎这是睡着了
Please keep your voice down.
世子小声些
My Lady finally fell asleep.
女郎好不容易才睡着
She'd been staying up for days.
女郎熬了好几日
Consort Yuanji and Madam Ruisheng were
世子妃和蕊夫人
worried that My Lady couldn't endure the strain
担心女郎大病初愈
so soon after her illness.
身子熬不住
Consort Yuanji just brought a bowl of calming soup
刚才世子妃端了碗安神汤来
and tricked My Lady into drinking it as ginseng soup.
骗女郎说是参汤喝下了
Now she's finally asleep.
眼下终于是睡着了
How can she sleep here?
在这里睡怎么能行
I'll carry her back to rest.
我抱她回去休息
Back... Back where?
回 回哪儿去啊
My Lady...
女郎
It seems the outcome of our bet is decided.
看来咱俩的赌约胜负已分
I'm going to win.
我要赢了
That's not right.
不对吧
I remember betting that they'd end up together.
我记得是我赌他俩能成
You always win bets with your husband
你跟你夫君打赌总赢
because you never own up when you lose, right?
是因为你输了就耍赖吧
That's not true!
我没有啊
Fine, I'll let you have your way.
成 耍赖也可以
How about letting Ziqi study
学文或是学医
both literature or medicine?
要不让子期都学吧
I think that's good.
我觉得可以
By the way,
对了
didn't you say His Highness got injured
你不是说世子
while getting bear gall
给嘉鱼妹妹取熊胆
for Jiayu?
受伤了吗
Can he carry someone now?
那他现在能抱人吗
Don't worry.
放心吧
He won't feel pain.
他不疼
True.
也是
Do you think Qing Long likes Yan Yue
你说青龙喜欢的是偃月
or Nanxing?
还是南星啊
I bet it's Yan Yue.
我赌是偃月
More bets?
还赌啊
This Phoenix Heart Token is different from my mother's.
这枚雀骨令和我阿母的不一样
If it's not with him, then...
不在他这儿 那么
Why did you sigh with relief?
为什么松了口气
I don't have Her Highness's Phoenix Heart Token.
郡主的雀骨令不在我的手上
I didn't kill Her Highness. Someone else did.
不是我杀的郡主 是别人
Who could it be?
是谁呢
Xie Jiayu, you're so smart.
谢嘉鱼 你这么聪明
You must already have an idea, right?
心中早有猜想了吧
Besides me,
除了我
of those by Her Highness's side,
在郡主身边的
who could do it and had a reason to do it?
能下手的 有理由下手的
How many suspects are still in your list?
你心中还剩下几个嫌疑人
If not me, it must be her
不是我 就只能是她
or them.
或是她们
You should be angry, furious,
你该愤怒 或生气
or confused.
或疑惑
So why did you sigh with relief?
那你为何偏偏松了口气呢
You're relieved it isn't me,
你不希望是我
aren't you?
是不是
Yaoyao,
夭夭
why do you feel so?
你为什么不希望呢
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
you're not completely in the clear yet.
你还没有完全洗清嫌疑
Since you already knew my motive,
你既然早知我目的
you could've hidden my mother's token
完全可以把我阿母的雀骨令
somewhere else.
藏在别的地方
If you suspect it's me,
你若怀疑是我
you can take my life at any time.
可随时取我性命
Do you think I dare not?
你以为我不敢吗
If I confess my love to you right now,
若我想此刻向你告白
would you think I'm a lunatic?
你会不会觉得我是个疯子
You are a lunatic.
你就是个疯子
Xie Jiayu...
谢嘉鱼
My heart belongs to you.
我心悦于你
I know...
我知道
♪ Weave our devotion into a melody of two hearts ♪
我知道郡主于你而言的意义
I'd never hurt the mother of the woman I love.
我不会伤害我心上人的母亲
Never.
决不会
♪ Know that your heart is my heart ♪
你受伤了
♪ Cherishing each other ♪
怎么回事
You didn't have this at Lingfeng Fort.
我记得在凌风堡的时候没有这个
What...
什么
Mother,
阿母
if you're watching from heaven,
您若是在天有灵
please bless me
就请保佑女儿
to find the culprit soon.
早日找到凶手吧
Someone made a move.
有人出手了
Who?
谁
Silly brother, let's go see Father.
笨阿兄 我们去见阿爹吧
Yes, let's go see Father.
对啊 我们去找阿爹
Memorials impeaching you
弹劾你的折子
are flooding the Censorate.
快堆满御史台了
Still won't hand Cui Jun over?
你还押着崔浚不交啊
The prison cart is making its way.
囚车在赶路呢
It rained and there was a landslide.
下雨了 滑坡
Traveling on the mountain is slow.
山路走得慢
Don't give me that nonsense.
你别跟我扯
I've known that Cui Jun had arrived in Jiankang.
我早就知道崔浚到了剑慷
He was just secretly imprisoned by you.
只不过被你秘密关押起来
Even if I hand over Cui Jun,
交不交出崔浚
the nobles won't try to impeach me any less.
世家弹劾我的奏折都不会少
You're just a witness in the Cui Family Case,
崔氏案你只是人证
escorting the Cui prisoners on the way.
顺便押送崔氏罪囚
Once in Jiankang,
到了剑慷
you have to hand them over to the Court of Judicial Review.
你就得提交到大理寺
Do you really want to pocket the Phoenix Heart Token
难不成你真想私吞雀骨令
and the Cui family's minerals?
和崔家矿产
Did Her Highness's death really have nothing to do with you?
郡主的死真跟你没关系
Seriously?
哥
It's not what I think.
这不是我说的
It's a rumor in the court,
是如今在朝堂中有所传言
saying Her Highness's death wasn't an accident,
说郡主的死啊 并非意外
but that you murdered her
而是你为了夺令
to seize her token.
蓄意谋害
If you don't hand over Cui Jun,
你若再不上交崔浚
the rumors will just worsen
恐怕再过几日
with each passing day.
谣言会更加离谱
The nobles are watching you like a hawk,
世家虎视眈眈
hoping to catch you slip up in any way.
就怕揪不住你的错处呢
Cui Jun hasn't confessed
崔浚还没有交代出
how to crack the token,
破解雀骨令的办法
so I can't hand him over.
还不能交
Yan Yue said that be it Zhuyou hypnosis,
偃月说无论是祝由催眠
poison, or torture,
还是毒药刑罚
he didn't say a word.
他都没有开口
The spy trained by the Empress Dowager of Northern Qin
北秦太后培养出的暗探
is indeed a character.
果真是个人物
Why is it you reporting this? Where's Yan Yue?
怎么你来报 偃月呢
What's wrong?
怎么了
Your Highness.
世子
What's going on?
怎么回事
Lady Xie said she wants to work on her martial arts,
谢娘子说要勤加习武
that mourning is no reason to slack off.
哪怕是孝期亦不可懈怠
What did she eat for breakfast?
早膳用了多少
Nothing.
未曾
Lady Xie heard that
谢娘子听闻
you do it on an empty stomach early in the morning,
世子早起练功时是空腹
and insisted on doing the same.
便也执意如此
Nonsense!
胡闹
Jiayu!
嘉鱼
Trying to starve yourself to death?
你想饿死是不是
What happened?
发生何事
Nothing.
没什么事
Have this.
来
Learning martial arts takes time.
习武非一日之功
It's good if you want to train.
你若真心想练习是好事
But you have to take it step by step,
但也需循序渐进
instead of rushing it, understand?
而非一日千里 知道吗
I just want to have something to do
我只是想给身体找点事做
so my mind can stop racing.
好让我的脑子停下来
Xie Jiayu.
谢嘉鱼
Stop mistreating yourself.
别再糟蹋自己了
You said your heart belongs to me.
你不是说你心悦于我吗
Then would you
那替我杀人
kill for me as well?
也可以吗
Princess Yunzhao just passed away.
郡主刚刚去了
But if you can't pull yourself together,
但你若不能让自己精神起来
no one else can be responsible for your life.
没有人可以对你的人生负责任
Not even you?
你也不行吗
I can kill for you.
我可以替你杀人
But I can't help you overcome this obstacle.
但我无法替你迈过眼前
You already know who did it,
你已经知道是谁动的手了
don't you?
是不是
Bad news, Your Highness!
不好了 世子
Cui Jun was taken away!
崔浚被人劫走了
What?
什么
The kidnapper left a message on the wall, saying they were
劫走他的人还在墙上落款说
acting on Crown Prince Wenxi's orders.
奉的是文熹太子之命
Impossible.
不可能
Don't go out for the next few days,
这几日你别出府
OK?
知道吗
My Lady.
女郎
The Heir arranged all this.
这些都是世子安排的
He said although you're not a real married couple,
世子说虽与女郎并非真夫妻
etiquette comes first.
但礼法在先
Princess Yunzhao is considered half an elder to him.
郡主也算是他半个长辈
For the mourning,
守丧之事
the estate should show its respects.
府里也该尽一份心意
The entire estate will mourn by wearing
全府上下以为主母服丧之礼
mourning clothes.
穿孝服
We've reported this to the Dowager Princess,
已经禀告过王妃
and she has agreed.
王妃也同意了
I just wonder
只是奇怪
why the Heir took so long to
世子既然有这份心
show this sincerity.
为何之前不派呢
He was afraid I wouldn't like it before.
之前是怕我不喜
But he's not afraid now?
今日又不怕了 为何
My heart belongs to you.
我心悦于你
My Lady, I don't think
女郎 奴婢觉得
the Heir did it.
不像是世子做的
I know he didn't do it.
我知道不是他做的
Someone wants me to think
是有人想让我认为
he killed her for her Phoenix Heart Token.
他是为了雀骨令而下的毒手
Crown Prince Wenxi is the hope of the people.
文熹太子是天下人的希望
Now that the token has appeared,
如今雀骨令出
Crown Prince Wenxi should naturally reveal himself.
文熹太子自然应当现世
Lejun, what are you doing here?
乐君 你在此处做什么呢
I was just about to call you for dinner.
正要叫你用晚膳呢
I lost my earring,
我耳坠掉了
so I came out to look for it.
就出来寻一寻
Did you find it?
那找到了吗
But
不过
Xiao Wuyi and my mother are
萧无衣和我阿母
indeed hiding something from me.
的确有事瞒着我
And my mother's death
而我阿母的死
is related to it.
也与之有关
It all started because of Crown Prince Wenxi.
一切都是因文熹太子而起
Xie, why are you here?
谢家丫头 你怎么来了
Your Highness.
王妃
You agreed to let the entire estate
王妃同意靖安王府上下
mourn for my mother.
为我阿母服丧
I should
这份心意
thank you in person.
嘉鱼该来拜谢
It's the least I could do.
都是应该的
Nanxing, take the things inside.
南星 你把东西拿到里面去
Yes.
诺
Your Highness,
王妃
you're also from the Capital.
您也是上京来的
There are some things about the past
有一些从前的事情
that I want to ask you.
我想问问您
Go ahead.
你问吧
I heard that my mother
听闻我阿母
used to be very close to Empress Wenxi;
从前和文熹皇后关系很好
close like sisters.
情同姐妹
Yes.
是
The Two Beauties of the Capital
昔年的上京双姝
referred to Empress Wenxi
说的就是文熹皇后
and Princess Yunzhao.
和云昭郡主
I also heard
那我又听说
that Old General Xiao
萧老将军
used to be a groom for Empress Wenxi's maternal family.
从前是文熹皇后母家的马夫
He entered the Imperial Guard because of Empress Wenxi's recommendation,
因文熹皇后推荐才进入禁军
and later led the Imperial Guard
后率领禁军
to escort the Ye royals and nobles to the south
护送大邺宗室和世家南渡
Establishing Southern Ye
建立南邺
and assisting the emperor,
有从龙之功
he was titled Prince Jing'an.
才受封靖安王
That is true.
的确如此
But why didn't
可我阿母
my mother ever mention the Xiao family
为何从来没有与我提起过萧家
or Old General Xiao to me?
也没有跟我说过萧老将军
They were of different social classes.
世庶尚有别
Not to mention the Prince was just a groom back then.
更何况王爷当年就是一介马夫
It's no surprise that
郡主不记得了
the Princess didn't remember him.
这也是情理当中的
But Empress Wenxi could entrust her last 50,000 Imperial Guards
可文熹皇后连最后的五万禁军
to Old General Xiao, so he must've been
都能交给萧老将军
a trusted confidant.
可称亲信
My mother was also someone Empress Wenxi trusted.
我阿母亦是文熹皇后信任之人
How could she not remember?
怎么会不记得
When Empress Wenxi gave birth to the Crown Prince on the brink of death,
当年文熹皇后临终前诞下太子
for some unknown reason,
不知什么原因
the Crown Prince failed to appear for a long time.
太子迟迟没有现身
So, the court was divided into two factions.
当时朝廷分为两派
One faction insisted on waiting for the Crown Prince to return
一派人坚持等到太子回朝
and supporting the orthodox heir,
扶立正统
such as your mother.
譬如你的阿母
The other faction was the various nobles,
另一派是各个世家
who advocated choosing a prince of similar age
他们主张从各个宗室
from the royal clans
选一个年龄相仿的王爷
and supporting him first.
先行扶立
The two factions were deadlocked.
两派僵持不下
Only Prince Jing'an, who commanded the Imperial Guard,
唯有手握禁军的王爷
had the right to decide.
有此决定权
The Prince chose the nobles
王爷选择了世家
and supported Emperor Rui,
扶持了睿帝
who is His Majesty's father.
也就是当今陛下的父皇
Yes.
是
Since then,
至此以后
the Princess and the Xiao family have had no contact.
郡主和萧氏家族再无往来
Then didn't the Prince have a Phoenix Heart Token?
那王爷没有雀骨令吗
I was just asking.
我就是随便问问
Well...
只是
My mother's token is missing.
我阿母的雀骨令丢了
Some say Xiao Wuyi killed my mother
有人说是萧无衣杀了我阿母
for her Phoenix Heart Token.
为的就是我阿母的雀骨令
That's why...
所以才
Impossible.
不可能
I can guarantee you that.
这一点我可以给你保证
Xiao Wuyi would never kill the Princess.
萧无衣绝对不会杀害郡主的
He couldn't...
他根本
Please believe me.
请你相信我
Wuyi would never kill the Princess.
无衣绝对不会杀害郡主的
You must trust Wuyi.
你要相信无衣
Don't let others mislead you.
你不要被别人挑唆了
I understand.
知道了 王妃
If you say so, I believe you.
您说了 我就信
I trust Xiao Wuyi.
我信萧无衣
Lady Xie,
谢娘子啊
please tell me
话说明白
why you're bringing me here.
你带我来这里做什么
Didn't I help you get
上次我不是助你
the chance to compete in archery?
得了走马穿杨比试的机会
You said you owed me a favor
你说欠我一个恩情
and would do one thing for me.
日后会答应我一件事情
I did say that.
我的确说过
Then ask no more.
那就不要再问
I promise this matter
我保证 这件事情
doesn't violate the laws of Ye.
绝不违反大邺律法
Sir, here he is.
先生 人给你带来了
Please hold out your hand.
请伸出手来
No.
不是
Thank you, sir.
多谢先生
What exactly is going on?
这到底是在做什么
"No" what?
什么不是
Wuyi?
无衣
You drew me.
你画的我
When was this? At the martial arts arena?
这又是哪一次 演武场吗
The bone reader said
摸骨人说了
you and Xiao Yao aren't biological brothers.
你和萧尧不是亲兄弟
So sure, huh?
这么笃定
What if he was wrong?
万一说错了呢
The fact that you're sitting here
你既然坐在这里
proves that I'm right.
那就证明我没有说错
When did you
你是什么时候
start doubting my identity?
开始怀疑我的身份的
At Lingfeng Fort.
凌风堡
That early?
这么早
At first,
一开始
I didn't care who Crown Prince Wenxi was.
我不在乎文熹太子是谁
I only cared about
我只在乎
who murdered my mother.
究竟是谁害了我阿母
I know my mother told you
我知道我阿母跟你说过
she'd trade the token for my freedom.
她用雀骨令换我自由身
The night before she died,
她出事之前那晚
I saw you two arguing.
我看到你们起了争执
She wouldn't
这雀骨令
give this token
她不会交给
to anyone other than Crown Prince Wenxi.
除了文熹太子之外的任何人
Since she promised you,
她既然答应过你
how could she go back on her word?
又怎会出尔反尔
That's why you suspected
所以一开始
that I was the one who attacked Her Highness
你才会怀疑是我对郡主出手
to get the token?
为了夺雀骨令
Besides you,
除了你
Lejun was also a probable suspect.
乐君也有理由
That day,
那日
I heard Her Highness arguing with someone.
我听见郡主在跟人争吵
She said she knew the whereabouts of Crown Prince Wenxi.
她说她知道文熹太子的下落
She was going to give the token
她要将雀骨令
to Crown Prince Wenxi.
交给文熹太子
In the carriage,
我在马车上
I did give her a chance.
不是没有给过她机会的
But she knew your background
可她知道你的身世
and insisted on helping Crown Prince Wenxi ascend the throne.
还坚持要辅佐文熹太子上位
If she heard my mother's desire
她如果听见我阿母
to support Crown Prince Wenxi's ascension,
想要扶持文熹太子上位
it'd pose a threat to Mao's position.
那就会对阿茂的地位产生威胁
So she also had a reason to take the token.
所以她也有理由夺令
Once Crown Prince Wenxi
一旦文熹太子
returns to Jiankang with the token,
带着雀骨令回到剑慷
what will you do, Brother?
哥哥你将如何自处
For the Eastern Palace,
为了这东宫之位
you even gave up Yaoyao.
你连夭夭都放弃了
I had to get rid of the ticking time bomb!
我不能留下这个隐患
Without Her Highness's token,
缺了郡主的这块雀骨令
even if Crown Prince Wenxi comes,
就算文熹太子来了
the prophecy is considered broken.
也算破了谶言
Who was she arguing with?
和她争执的人是谁
I didn't see clearly, but I think...
我没看清楚 但我猜
it must be Xiao Wuyi.
是萧无衣
Xiao Wuyi really wants the token.
萧无衣他很想要雀骨令
He's been holding on to Cui Jun's token.
崔浚那枚就一直握在他手上
Brother.
哥哥
In my opinion,
依妹妹看
to Xiao Wuyi,
在萧无衣心中
you're just a pawn kept in the imperial government
你就是他推行北府改制
to facilitate the Beifu Reform.
留在中枢的一枚棋子
If he dares to fall in love with Yaoyao,
他现在既然敢对夭夭动情
how much affection
那对哥哥你
does he have left for you?
又还留有几分情谊呢
You must never...
万不可
trust Xiao Wuyi again.
再信萧无衣
Only you have the grain that could
能控制马匹发狂的稻谷
drive a horse mad.
只有你有
So at first,
所以一开始
I was more suspicious of you.
我对你的怀疑更大
When did it change?
那又是什么时候变了呢
On the day of the wedding,
大婚那日
the one who died was my twin brother.
死的是我孪生兄长
My brother and I were
我兄弟二人
secret guards raised by Princess Yunzhao.
都是郡主供养的暗卫
Up until the wedding,
直到大婚之前
our existence was
我二人的存在
unknown even to the Grand Tutor.
就连太傅都不知晓
Aren't you dead?
你不是死了吗
Before Mother went to Lingfeng Fort,
阿母去凌风堡之前
she sent him on an errand.
令他外出办差
But by the time he returned,
但等他回来的时候
Mother was already killed.
阿母已经出事了
When we entered the city that day, I stayed behind
那日入城 我留下来
just to tell Li Mao that
就是为了告诉李茂
I've found a witness.
我已经找到证人了
Lejun is severely injured and unconscious.
乐君如今重伤未醒
If she wakes up,
她若是醒来后
ask her to think carefully
你让她帮我仔细想一想
if there are any other witness clues.
还有没有什么人证线索
I had someone look for the groom's family,
我让人去找了马夫的家人
hoping to find some new clues.
希望能有什么新线索
Then, My Lady
随后
ordered me to immediately take control
女郎令我立刻控制住
of the groom's family
马夫的家人
and bring them to Jiankang,
送来剑慷
to see if anyone
就是要看看
would take the opportunity to act.
有没有人会趁机动手
As expected, Prince Qi's men came.
果然 岐王的人来了
So you suspected Li Lejun early on.
所以你早就开始怀疑李乐君
They took the bait.
愿者上钩
I just cast the hook for everyone.
我只是给所有人都下了钩
Luring the snake out of its hole
引蛇出洞
also alerts the snake.
同样也是打草惊蛇
Li Mao and Li Lejun
李茂和李乐君
must've noticed your suspicion,
必然察觉了你的怀疑
and will soon find out that
也很快会发现
the groom's family
马夫的家人
actually know nothing
其实什么都不知道
and aren't witnesses.
且并非人证
So what if they know?
他们知道又如何
Alright.
好
Then let's talk about me.
那聊聊我吧
When exactly did I give myself away?
我到底是什么时候露出了马脚
When Cui Jun took my mother hostage.
崔浚劫持我阿母的时候
Crown Prince Wenxi died long ago!
文熹太子早死了
He didn't die!
他没有死
Cui Jun was taken away.
崔浚被人劫走了
The kidnapper left a message on the wall, saying they were
劫走他的人还在墙上落款说
acting on Crown Prince Wenxi's orders.
奉的是文熹太子之命
Impossible.
不可能
Being overly certain is
过分笃定
indeed inappropriate.
确实不妥
Once suspicion arises,
怀疑一旦产生
it can't be curbed.
就无法停止
Xiyue Restaurant keeps telling stories
西月楼一直在说雀骨令
about the token and Crown Prince Wenxi.
和文熹太子的话本子
If Crown Prince Wenxi is really alive,
这文熹太子要真活着
how old would he be?
该多大年纪啊
Twenty-four years ago... So, 24.
二十四年前 那就是二十四岁
The Dowager Princess's contradictory attitude towards you...
老王妃对你矛盾的态度
Wuyi is also my son.
无衣也是我的儿子
Then why refuse to go see Xiao Wuyi?
那您为何不肯看看萧无衣
Xiao Wuyi would never kill the Princess.
萧无衣绝对不会杀害郡主的
And Mother's blind trust in you
还有我阿母在崔家时
when she was at the Cui Mansion.
对你无端的信任
Who says we stand alone?
岂曰无衣
We share weal and woe.
与子同袍
He indeed
他的确给自己
gave himself a very nice name.
取了个很好的名字
Also,
还有
her evaluation of Crown Prince Wenxi.
她对文熹太子的评价
Mother said Crown Prince Wenxi is
阿母说文熹太子
someone who values the world
是一个将天下
more than himself,
看得比自身重的人
who spares no effort for this world,
他为了这天下不惜己身
and that those who can bear this saying
能担得起这句话的人
are few in this world.
全天下没有几个
I happen to know
而这样的疯子
a lunatic of such a caliber.
我恰好认识一个
Xie Jiayu,
谢嘉鱼
so you have such a high opinion of me.
原来你对我的评价这么高啊
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
it's time to reveal your true identity.
你该以真面目示人了
Yes.
是
I am Crown Prince Wenxi.
我的确是文熹太子
It's time to bring Mother home.
是时候去接阿母了
Nanxing, help me with my grooming and dressing.
南星 帮我梳妆更衣吧
Over the years,
这些年
my Xie family had received so much favor from the Princess.
谢氏承了郡主多少恩情
My Shanji Hall could
我的善济堂
stay open thanks to the Princess's
也是靠郡主多年的资助
years of financial support.
才能开得下去
These Buddhist scriptures were
这些佛经
hand-copied by the women and children
是善济堂这几日
of Shanji Hall these few days
妇孺们亲自抄写
to be offered to the Princess.
一起献给郡主
Offer condolences!
谢吊
Princess Pingning has arrived.
平宁县主到
Greetings, Your Highness.
见过县主
My brother and I've had a tough life.
乐君与哥哥自幼孤苦
Thankfully, the Princess took care of us.
幸有郡主照拂
We're forever indebted to her.
此恩难报
I have requested a decree
乐君已请旨
to be an escort for the Princess.
前来为郡主扶灵
Greetings, Grand Tutor.
见过太傅
Doing this even when you're injured.
县主有伤在身
This is very thoughtful of you.
实在是有心了
It's time!
时辰到
Start the procession! Break the bowl!
起灵 摔瓦
Wait!
慢着
Father,
阿父
with me around,
我还在
how can my cousin break the bowl
怎么能让堂兄来摔盆
and an outsider be the escort?
再让外人来扶灵
Lejun fell down the cliff with my mother,
乐君与我阿母一同摔下悬崖
yet she recovered so quickly.
竟好得如此之快
It seems
可见
you're very blessed.
福泽深厚啊
Yaoyao, I'm sorry.
夭夭 对不起
I didn't hold onto the Princess.
是我没拉住郡主
If only I had moved faster that day.
当日我动作若是快些就好了
Yaoyao, where have you been?
夭夭 你怎么才来呀
It's been past the 7 days of mourning,
这都过了头七了
and you haven't been kneeling by the coffin.
这几日也不见你跪灵
I forbade her from coming.
是我不让她来的
I thought I made it very clear last time
我上次应该说得很清楚
that you're not allowed to set foot in the Xie Mansion!
不许你踏进谢府半步
Everyone, you may not know,
诸位或许有所不知
but my mother had divorced my father.
我阿母已与阿父和离
Mother wouldn't want...
按照我阿母的意愿
Divorced?
和离
To be buried in the Xie ancestral graveyard.
定是不愿入谢氏祖坟
So today,
故而今日
I'm here to take her away.
我来带她走
How insolent!
放肆
Jiayu,
嘉鱼丫头
you can't just spout nonsense.
这话可不能乱说
How could your parents be divorced?
你阿父阿母怎么可能和离
I have two letters in my hand.
我手中有两封信
This letter was
这一封
written to me by my mother when she left Jiankang.
是我阿母离开剑慷时写给我的
She said she'd divorced my father
她说她已经和阿父和离
and wanted to go out to relax
想要出去散散心
and travel the world.
游历这天下
The second letter...
第二封
was written to my father when my mother was
是阿母在凌风堡时
at Lingfeng Fort.
写给阿父的
These are the Princess's belongings.
这些是郡主的遗物
Unfortunately, she died
只可惜还没来得及寄出
before she could mail it.
就已经出事了
Father,
阿父
want to take a look?
你要看看吗
No need.
我不必看
My marriage to your mother
我和你阿母的婚事
was decreed by the royals.
乃皇家赐婚
So, without verification of the Clan Court
所以若无宗正稽核
and the approval of the Inner Court,
内廷允准
your divorce paper is
你的和离书根本就
utterly invalid.
毫无公用啊
Since the entire Xie family is gathered here today,
趁今日谢氏族人都在
I will say it again:
我就再说一遍
Xie Jiayu is not Yunzhao's and my biological child!
谢嘉鱼并非我与云昭亲生
-What?
这 这
-What's this? -I don't know.
怎么 不知道
She is just
她只是云昭
an orphan Yunzhao picked up from somewhere.
捡回来的孤儿罢了
A little pet
被云昭
kept by Yunzhao for just over a decade.
当猫儿狗儿养了十几年而已
So, what right...
所以她凭什么
What right does she have
她凭什么
to make decisions for my Xie family and Yunzhao?
做我谢氏和云昭的主
Let's not waste any more time.
别再耽误时辰了
T-This...
这 这
Did Prince Jing'an's Mansion raise a bunch of bandits?
靖安王府是养了一群土匪吗
Barging into my Xie mourning hall
跑到我谢氏的灵堂上
to snatch the coffin, huh?
来抢棺椁
Is there
这
still any law and order?
还有王法吗
Grand Tutor.
太傅
Xie Jiayu's word is law
今日谢嘉鱼的话
today.
便如军令
I hope you can let Jiayu finish what she has to say.
还望太傅听嘉鱼把话说完
Cui Jun is a secret spy of Northern Qin.
崔浚乃北秦暗探
After Mother was controlled by him,
阿母被其控制后
she had a chance to escape.
本有机会逃脱
But she heard Cui Jun mention the An-Lu case.
但她听崔浚提起了安陆之案
To pry the truth
为了从崔浚口中探出
out of Cui Jun,
安陆之案的真相
Mother spared no effort to deal with him
阿母不惜与他周旋
and almost couldn't get away.
差点脱不了身
Mother knew that
阿母知道
the An-Lu case was a lifelong emotional burden of yours.
安陆之案乃你此生心结
You need closure.
不解开 难释怀
So she'd rather risk her life
所以她宁愿以身冒险
just to seek the truth for you.
也想为你求一个真相
Mother once thought
阿母曾经以为
your obsessions were all wrong.
你的执念都是错的
Only later did she know she was wrong too.
后来才知她也错了
Now,
现在
the truth is in my hands.
真相就在我手里
Yaoyao!
夭夭
Don't!
别
Grand Tutor!
太傅
I said to
我说了
let Xie Jiayu finish speaking today.
今日请听谢嘉鱼把话说完
Father.
阿父
My mother was murdered.
我阿母是被人害死的
Do you dare to let me investigate
您敢让我去查
who really murdered my mother?
到底是谁害了我阿母吗
Xie Jiayu, the nerve of you to say this.
谢嘉鱼 你还真有脸说这话
It was clearly because the horse got spooked
明明是马匹受惊
that your mother had that accidental fall.
你阿母才意外坠马
If you hadn't swapped carriages with her,
但要不是你跟她换马车
it would've been you instead.
出意外的本该就是你
What else is there to investigate?
还有什么好查的呢
Fine, I understand.
好 我明白了
If you don't want to investigate,
阿父不想查
I'll do it myself.
我自己查
I'll get justice for my mother.
还我阿母一个公道
Let me ask you again, Father.
我再问阿父
If I want to exchange the An-Lu case for Mother,
若我要以安陆之案换我阿母
will you make the trade or not?
阿父换还是不换
No, no, you...
不 不 你这
Father.
阿父
Will you make the trade or not?
换还是不换
No! Don't, don't!
不 别别别
If there's any truth to the An-Lu case,
若安陆之案有真相可言
then that's a matter of state!
那这 那就是国事啊
How can you jeopardize the state
你岂能凭一己之私
for your own selfish interests?
毁家国大事呢
Is that so?
是吗
Then Father,
那阿父
in the repeating crossbow case,
当日连环弩之案
didn't you jeopardize the state
您难道没有为一己之私
for your own selfish interests?
毁家国大事
Nonsense!
不可妄言
What does your father have to do with the repeating crossbow?
你阿父和连环弩有什么关系
Whether I'm speaking nonsense,
我是不是妄言
Father knows best.
阿父心里最清楚
Whether I want to burn everything down with me,
我是不是真的想鱼死网破
Father also knows best.
阿父心里也清楚
Mother told me
阿母同我讲了
your past stories.
你们过去的故事
Since you love someone else,
既然您心中另有所爱
since even the beginning was a mistake,
既然连开始都是错的
then why wouldn't you let Mother be free?
那您为什么不肯放阿母一个自由
From the Capital to Jiankang,
从上京到剑慷
too many people are
困于过往
trapped in the past and in the court.
困于朝廷之人太多
Mother is gone.
阿母已经去了
I just want her
我只想为她
to find peace in the afterlife.
还一个身后自在
How could you—how could anyone—
我对云昭之爱
understand my love for Yunzhao?
岂是你 岂是任何人能懂
She was the one
当年是她自己
who chose the wrong beginning.
选择了错误的开始
Since it was wrong,
既然错
then it must be wrong till the end.
那就只能错到底
That's what she owed me.
那是她欠我的
I'll trade!
我换
Mother was right.
阿母说得没错
Nothing...
任何事情
can outweigh the An-Lu case
都抵不过安陆之案
in your heart.
在阿父心中的分量
Today, the entire Xie family is here.
今日谢氏族人都在
Please be my witnesses.
那就请诸位做个见证
Mother wrote a divorce paper long ago,
我阿母早已写下和离书
and Father has agreed to it today.
阿父今日也同意了
From now on,
从此
Princess Yunzhao and the Xie family have no further ties,
云昭郡主与谢氏再无瓜葛
parting amicably.
一别两宽
Even if...
就算
you take Yunzhao away today,
你今日带走云昭
without the Emperor and Empress Dowager annulling the marriage,
无陛下 太后解除赐婚
she, Li Fuhua,
她李甫华
will always be my wife!
永远都是我的妻子
Her soul will
她的魂魄
never leave the Xie ancestral hall!
永远都离不开谢氏祠堂
You don't need to worry about that, Father.
这就不劳阿父操心了
Father.
阿父
This is the last time I'll call you Father.
这也是我最后唤您一声阿父